Guide to the Camilo José Vergara Photographs, 1977-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Camilo José Vergara photographs 1977-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Vergara, Camilo J.
5.0 linear feet Extent: 87 Items
Camilo J. Vergara is a documentary photographer, focusing on the evolution of urban spaces. Collection of color prints from Vergara's 2009 National Building Museum exhibit Storefront Churches, with photographs of urban churches, pasters, and murals from cities around the United States. This exhibit was part of a larger collection featured in Vergara's book, How the Other Half Worships.
RL.01330
Language: Material in English, and Spanish
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted to educational, non-commercial use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Camilo José Vergara Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2010.
Biographical Note
Camilo José Vergara is a New York-based photographer documenting the changing urban landscape of inner cities throughout the United States. He began focusing on urban neighborhoods in the 1970s, and since then has published numerous photography compilations and essays. Vergara is known for his ability to capture transition within a city and its structures, such as the re-use of buildings and their eventual abandonment and reclamation by nature. His titles include Silent Cities: The Evolution of the American Cemetery, The New American Ghetto, American Ruins, Twin Towers Remembered, and How the Other Half Worships.
Vergara earned a B.A. in sociology from the University of Notre Dame (1968) and a M.A. in sociology from Columbia University (1977). He has received several awards for his work, including a 2002 MacArthur Foundation genius grant.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of 85 color prints, ranging in size from 11x14 inches to 20x24 inches, as well as two 30x30 color transparencies. These images were all part of the National Building Museum's 2009 Vergara exhibit, Storefront Churches, and many are also featured in his recent book, How the Other Half Worships (2005).
Subjects include urban churches in cities throughout the United States, in particular New York City and its neighborhoods (such as Harlem, Brooklyn, and the Bronx), Detroit, Chicago, Los Angeles, Gary, and Camden. Vergara's photographs vary in what part of each church is highlighted: some are simply the church's exterior, offering a glimpse of the neighborhood and condition of the building; other images are taken inside the church, whether it be an abandoned sanctuary or an active praise service. The collection also contains, to a lesser extent, photographs of religious and spiritually-inspired murals and artwork from different urban environments; cemeteries and outdoor worship spaces; and some portraits of different pastors and preachers, including street preachers. Most of the churches represented in the collection are Pentecostal, Baptist, or some other branch of Evangelical Protestant Christianity.
The collection documents the evolution of church structures, such as the series of rephotography of a Chicago building that evolved from the Holy Raiders Revival Church in 1981 to the Mt. Zion Missionary Baptist Church in 2009. Vergara rephotographed the building six times during that period, and each time the building's facade and surroundings had changed significantly. Vergara's photographs also offer one-time glimpses of abandoned and decaying buildings, as well as documentation of reclaimed and re-used urban structures, such as the former Kentucky Fried Chicken restaurant that is now a worship center in Newark.
Collection Arrangement
This collection has been arranged and boxed by the size of the photograph, and is not organized by subject or date. Vergara's captions frequently include the street address for the structures or people he photographed; these addresses are noted when available. In addition, frequently the church's name was not included in Vergara's caption, but is visible in the photograph. In this case, the church name has been added to the description below. The collection's oversize transparencies are undated and unlabeled, and have been boxed separately.
Contents of Collection
- 11x14 color prints, (1 box)
  - Greater True Friendship Baptist Church, 2002 (Box 1)
    1842 W. Vernon, Los Angeles, California
  - Mount Gaza Baptist Church, 2003 (Box 1)
    1004 Whitemarsh at Raymond, Compton, California
  - Iglesia de la Profesia, 2003 (Box 1)
    11th St. at Linden, Camden, New Jersey
  - St. Martin Morning Star, 2006 (Box 1)
    3416 W. 29th St., Gary, Indiana
  - Iglesia de Dios Pentecostal la Senda Divina, former Kentucky Fried Chicken, 2003 (Box 1)
    585 Broadway, Newark, New Jersey
  - Moorish Science Temple of America No. 25, 2008 (Box 1)
    Grand River Blvd. at Hudson
  - Gospel Church According to Christ Ministries, 2002 (Box 1)
    E. Monument Ave. at N. East Ave., Baltimore, Maryland
  - General Assembly Church/House of Mercy Mission, 2002 (Box 1)
    Springfield Ave. at Pierce Street, Newark, New Jersey
  - Pastor Green's church, Rev. Denson by the entrance. Fellowship M.B.C. Church, 2002 (Box 1)
    410 E. 31st St., Los Angeles, California
  - Congregation Ahawath Joseph, 1977 (Box 1)
    Paterson, New Jersey
  - Pastor Gloria Lawton, New Life in the Great I Am Church, 2004 (Box 1)
    Bostwick Ave., Jersey City, New Jersey
  - Mother Downs, House of Blessings, 1991 (Box 1)
    5440 S. State St., Chicago, Illinois
  - Evangelista Martin Capeles, 2004 (Box 1)
    Southern Blvd., Bronx, New York
  - Church sign with missing letters, 2000 (Box 1)
    2291 Ersbine St., Detroit, Michigan
  - Little Widow's Mite B.C. Church sign, 2004 (Box 1)
    E. 147th St. at Willis Ave., S. Bronx, New York
  - Home of Life Missionary Baptist Church, 2003 (Box 1)
    4650 W. Madison St., Chicago, Illinois
  - Sam preaching, 2003 (Box 1)
    5th St., Skid Row, Los Angeles, California
  - Iglesia Evangelica de Jesucristo Betania, 2003 (Box 1)
    1219 E. Adams Blvd., Los Angeles, California
  - Iglesia Pentacostal Jehova Jreh Inc., 2003 (Box 1)
    2842 Germantown Ave., Philadelphia, Pennsylvania
  - St. Martins Spiritual Baptist Church, 2002 (Box 1)
    162A Utica Ave., Brooklyn, New York
  - Red building with cross window, 1979 (Box 1)
    S. Camden, New Jersey
  - Hermanas Pura y Juara, Dominican, Iglesia Sen da de Bendecion, 2001 (Box 1)
    506 Brook Ave., S. Bronx, New York
  - Tabernacle Missionary Baptist Church, 2006 (Box 1)
    Grand River Blvd. at Dexter, Detroit, Michigan
  - Jesus Christ Saves, Heals, Delivers truck, 2006 (Box 1)
    Grant St. at N. 6th St., Camden, New Jersey
  - Lawrence Moore preaching on the corner, 2004 (Box 1)
    6th St. at San Pedro, Skid Row, Los Angeles, California
  - Mision Cristiana Pentacostes el Amor de Cristo, 1999 (Box 1)
    6419 S. Crenshaw Blvd., Los Angeles, California
  - Triumph: The Church and Kingdom of God in Christ, 2004 (Box 1)
    824 W. 25th St., Gary, Indiana
  - Iglesia Pentacostal Sendero de Luz, 2002 (Box 1)
    612 Union Ave., Bronx, New York
  - Pure in Heart, 2000 (Box 1)
    14849 Livernois Ave., Detroit, Michigan
  - When Everything Fails Try Prayer sign, 2003 (Box 1)
    5258 S. Indiana Ave., Chicago, Illinois
  - If You are Going to the Jail Court or Hospital Call for Prayer sign, 2004 (Box 1)
    W. Lake St., Chicago, Illinois
  - God Tabernacle of Faith, 1996 (Box 1)
    65th St., Los Angeles, California
  - Sacred Heart Garden, Missionaries of the Charity, 1989 (Box 1)
    E. 167th St., Bronx, New York
  - Sacred Heart Seminary, 2003 (Box 1)
    2701 Chicago Ave., Detroit, Michigan
  - Zion Lutheran Church wall, 2008 (Box 1)
    4305 Military St., Detroit, Michigan
  - Una Luz en el Cavino, 2004 (Box 1)
    Concord Ave., Bronx, New York
  - Harvest Crusade billboard, Greater St. Paul Baptist Church, 2004 (Box 1)
    International Ave. at 5th Ave., Oakland, California
  - Mural by Elliott Pinkney, 1987 (Box 1)
    Compton Ave. at 36th St., Los Angeles, California
  - St. Cyril and St. Methodius Church, 2003 (Box 1)
    St. Cyril St., Detroit, Michigan
  - Deacon E.M. McGee, New Jerusalem Baptist Church, 1998 (Box 1)
    3123 Halsted, Chicago, Illinois
  - Holy Raiders Revival Church, 1981 (Box 1)
    4344 W. Madison St., Chicago, Illinois
  - Holy Raiders Revival Church, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Holy Raiders Revival Church, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Holy Raiders Revival Church, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Mt. Zion Missionary Baptist Church, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Mt. Zion Missionary Baptist Church, 2009 (Box 1)
  - International Christian Lifestyle, 2004 (Box 1)
    1585 Fillmore St., Gary, Indiana
- 16x20 color prints, (1 box)
  - Thank God for Jesus Church, 2002 (Box 2)
    1600 N. Bond St., Baltimore, Maryland
  - Street Evangelist, 2008 (Box 2)
    Adam Clayton Powell at W. 116th St., Harlem, New York
  - Prayer Tabernacle of the Apostalic Faith, 2000 (Box 2)
    9101 S. Western Ave., Los Angeles, California
  - Everlasting Church of God in Christ, 2002 (Box 2)
    12107 Kinsman Rd., Cleveland, Ohio
  - Greater Love Christian Center Church, 2001 (Box 2)
    514 W. 71st St., Chicago, Illinois
  - Former City Methodist Church, 1998 (Box 2)
    6th Ave. at Washington St., Gary, Indiana
  - Tree of Life mural (12x12 print), undated (Box 2)
- 20x24 color prints, (1 box)
  - New Creation Ministries, 2003 (Box 3)
    Sutter at Sheffield Ave., Brooklyn, New York
  - Rock Church, 2007 (Box 3)
    Broadway at 8th Ave., Gary, Indiana
  - Anthony Ray, The Greater Temple of Praise, 2002 (Box 3)
    153 Snediken, Brooklyn, New York
  - New Jerusalem Baptist Church, Christ from the Apocalypses, 2002 (Box 3)
    4923 S. Western Ave., Los Angeles, California
  - Mural of Jesus and his disciples, over a doorway, 1992 (Box 3)
    Garfield Ave., West of Normal, Chicago, Illinois
  - Mt. Paran Baptist Church, 2008 (Box 3)
    Corner of Broadway and Shaffer, Brooklyn, New York
  - Inner City Gospel Ministry mural, 1994 (Box 3)
    Cari Ave. at Temple St., Detroit, Michigan
  - Supernatural Deliverance Revival Tabernacle, 2003 (Box 3)
    70 1st St., Newark, New Jersey
  - Mural of crucified Jesus, 2003 (Box 3)
    Evergreen St. at Menahan St., Brooklyn, New York
  - Life of the Valley Spiritual Church, 2002 (Box 3)
    257 W. 48th Place, Chicago, Illinois
  - Pastor Ashford, True Gospel Church of the Living God, 2004 (Box 3)
    1855 Third Ave., Richmond, California
  - Tabernaculo de fe Iglesia de Dios en Cristo, 1996 (Box 3)
    Hoover St. at 65th St., Los Angeles, California
  - Dorian at New Friendship M.B. Church, 2003 (Box 3)
    3620-3622 139th St., Harvey, Illinois
  - Anointment by Bishop Wallace Furns, America Come Back to God, 2004 (Box 3)
    Rockaway Ave. by Gutter, Brooklyn, New York
  - Wooden cross, 2006 (Box 3)
    Chloe Ave. at Frederick St., Detroit, Michigan
  - Christ Temple House of Prayer Deliverance Church, after Sunday service, 2007 (Box 3)
    405 Malcolm X Blvd., Harlem, New York
  - New Testament Baptist Church, 2002 (Box 3)
    13311 Mack Ave., Detroit, Michigan
  - New Jerusalem Baptist Church, 1992 (Box 3)
    7133 S. Halsted, Chicago, Illinois
  - Church of Gospel Ministries, 2000 (Box 3)
    S. Main St. at 70th St., Los Angeles, California
  - Praises of Zion Baptist Church, 2006 (Box 3)
    1722 55th St., Oakland, California
  - View North towards Florence, 2005 (Box 3)
    7th St., Camden, New Jersey
  - Devil's Juice mural by John B. Downey, Emmanuel Baptist Rescue Mission, 2003 (Box 3)
    Crocker at 5th St., Skid Row, Los Angeles, California
  - Pentacostal House of Prayer, 2004 (Box 3)
    4143 W. Madison St., Chicago, Illinois
  - St. James Apostelic Church, a former Broadway Trust, 2003 (Box 3)
    Broadway at Walnut St., Camden, New Jersey
  - St. Francis of Assisi R.C. Church, built in 1903. View East, 2009 (Box 3)
    Hammond at Buchanan, Detroit, Michigan
  - True Vine Temple of Christ, 2000 (Box 3)
    4155 St. Aubin, Detroit, Michigan
  - Evergreen Cemetery, tombstone photographs of Rev. William H. Rozier, founder of the Pleasant Hill Baptist Church (died 1937), May 1985 (Box 3)
    Boyle Heights, Los Angeles, California
  - Emmanuel Baptist Rescue Mission mural by John B. Downey, 2003 (Box 3)
    5th St. at Crocker St., Skid Row, Los Angeles, California
  - Former Werth's Appliance Center, 2000 (Box 3)
    State St., Hammond, Indiana
  - Antioch Independent Church of God in Christ sign, 2003 (Box 3)
    547 S. 19th St., Newark, New Jersey
- 30x30 transparencies, (1 box)
  Consists of 2 oversize transparencies. These are not labeled or dated.
  - Jesus Never Fails neon sign (Box 4)
  - Stained glass cross (Box 4)